Waco Public Library Association records, Inclusive: 1856-1925, undated, Bulk: 1898-1921, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Waco Public Library Association records
Inclusive: 1856-1925, undated, Bulk: 1898-1921, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2041
Waco Public Library Association
13 folders.
The Waco Public Library Association records trace the formation and continuing operations of the first Waco Public Library, funded in part by Andrew Carnegie.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
The Waco Public Library Association records trace the formation and continuing operations of the first Waco Public Library, funded in part by philanthropist Andrew Carnegie. The Waco Public Library Association was formed on 1898 May 4, intending to furnish Waco with its first public library. In 1899, using circulars, benefits, and other means of raising financial support, the Association founded a library of 600 books in a rented cottage at 116 North Eighth Street. The library officially opened to the public on 1900 January 22.
The library soon grew out of its small home, however, and the Association wrote to Andrew Carnegie for potential financial backing. Carnegie, who eventually built 32 such libraries in Texas, agreed to donate $30,000 if a site and $3,000 of yearly support could be obtained from the City of Waco. The city government agreed, and a Building Committee with local businessman William Herman Hoffman Sr. at its head was formed. The new Carnegie Library, with some 3,200 books, opened in Waco on 1904 November 28. Although the original Carnegie building was eventually demolished, the Waco Public Library system remains strong today; its board is now called the Waco-McLennan County Library Advisory Commission. The Waco Public Library Association Records will prove to be an excellent research for anyone interested in the history of Waco, Progressive Era philanthropy, Carnegie Libraries, or the development of a public library from the ground up.
Scope and Content
The Waco Public Library Association records consist of correspondence, legal documents, financial materials, scrapbooks, and literary productions related to the Waco Public Library Association. Of particular note is a set of correspondence seeking funding from Andrew Carnegie to found the first Waco Public Library building.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid, the Waco Public Library Association records were organized into folders by material type. Some folder titles have been preserved.
Currently, the collection is organized into five series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, III. Financial Materials, IV. Scrapbook, and V. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2041. Acquired 1979-10-18
Related Resources
Related references
Bobinski, George S. Carnegie Libraries; Their History and Impact on American Public Library Development. Chicago: American Library Association, 1969.
City of Waco Municipal Information. “Boards and Commissions.” The City of Waco. Accessed 2014 May 30.
“Library Has Colorful History.” Waco Citizen, 1981 August 29.
Terri Jo Ryan. “Brazos Past: Carnegie Library Made ‘Athens on the Brazos’ Accessible to All.” Waco Tribune. March 5, 2013, sec. Waco History. Accessed 2014 May 30.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919.
Subjects (Organizations)
Waco-McLennan County Library -- History.
Places
Waco (Tex.) -- History.
Subjects
Carnegie libraries -- Texas.; Progressivism (United States politics) -- History -- 20th century.; Public libraries -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Membership lists.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1898-1925, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence regarding fundraising for the Waco Public Library, including communication with other Carnegie libraries. Also included are mailing lists of potential supporters and donors.
  - Correspondence, 1898-1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1905-1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mailing Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Legal Documents, 1856-1904; 2
  This series contains legal documents regarding the new Waco Public Library including business and architectural contracts.
  - Legal Documents, 1856-1904 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Financial Materials, 1902-1904, undated; 3
  This series contains financial materials related to the fundraising associated with the development of a new library.
  - Financial Materials, 1902-1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Scrapbooks, 1917-1918; 4
  General condition: Good.
  This series contains a scrapbook of press clippings related to the Waco library.
  - Scrapbooks, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Literary Productions, 1901-1912, undated; 5
  This series includes reports, membership lists, clippings, circulars, and other printed materials related to the Waco Public Library Association.
  - Reports, 1901-1902, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Membership Lists, 1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1901-1921 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General, 1902-1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)